

# Louis Lippens

DOCTORAL PESEARCHE

Ghent University (FEB), Sint-Pietersplein 6, 9000 Gent, Belgium

☑ Louis.Lippens@UGent.be | 备 louislippens.be | ☑ Louis-Lippens | ☑ Iglip | 🛅 louislippens

# **About Me**

I am a joint **PhD researcher** in **labour economics** and **sociology of labour** at Ghent University and Vrije Universiteit Brussel with an **inter-disciplinary background** and a pronounced interest in data visualisation. My present work focuses on the determinants of and contextual factors contributing to **(ethnic) hiring discrimination**. More broadly, I research labour market topics relating to **hiring and selection** and **labour demand and supply**. I have previously worked for consulting firms on data governance, data analytics, and HR projects. I have also obtained a master's degree in **work psychology** and a business degree in **general management**.

# **Employment**

# ACADEMIA (FULL-TIME)

Ghent University Ghent, BE

DOCTORAL RESEARCHER Aug. 2019 – Present

- Research on topics in labour economics (90
- Teaching assignments (10
- Development of low-threshold, interactive, and flexible tools (e.g. multicultural situational judgment tests) to increase the awareness of HR professionals' intercultural competence and to empower them to deal with the drivers of their competence
- · Dissertation: research on (ethnic) hiring discrimination, its determinants, its mechanisms, and the influence of the organisational context

Vrije Universiteit Brussel

Brussels, BE

VISITING DOCTORAL RESEARCHER

Aug. 2019 – Present

· Research on topics in sociology of labour

## PRIVATE SECTOR (FULL-TIME)

BDO Ghent/Antwerp/Brussels, BE

SENIOR CONSULTANT (DATA ANALYTICS)

Oct. 2018 - Jul. 2019

- Performed survey research on the modal shift in transportation and developed a predictive model for a governmental body and an inland port
- · Advised a private company active in the entertainment industry on the design of a data asset repository
- Constructed a financial model for a mid-scale mobility management project

Capgemini Invent Brussels, BE

CONSULTANT (DATA GOVERNANCE)

Sep. 2017 - Sep. 2018

Sep. 2015 - Jan. 2016

- Performed a benchmark study of data governance operating models in financial services
- Developed and optimised various data asset documentation processes in the context of BCBS239 and GDPR regulatory frameworks
- Conducted a data quality maturity assessment across various business and functional departments within a major Belgian bank
- · Set up data-sharing agreements between various business and functional departments within a major Belgian bank

### INTERNSHIPS (FULL-TIME)

HR CONSULTANT

CEMAC Ghent, BE

May 2017 – Jun. 2017

- Redesign of the firm's organisational structure and internal business processes
- · Analysis of the firm's product strategy and internationalisation opportunities and capabilities

The Future Alliance Ghent, BE

• Organised assessment and development centres for middle management candidates

- Organised workshops concerning HR-related topics (e.g. giving and receiving feedback)
- Carried out recruitment and selection assignments for entry and (middle) management functions

JUN 2022 LOUIS LIPPENS · RESUME 1 OF 5

Hudson Ghent, BE

HR CONSULTANT Oct. 2014 - Nov. 2014

Developed 40 rating scales, including a manual, for the advisory firm's dedicated competency model

## SOCIAL SECTOR (PART-TIME)

**180 Degrees Consulting** Ghent, BE

• 180 Degrees Consulting (180DC) is the world's largest international consultancy for non-profits and social enterprises

- Led the human capital activities of 180DC's Ghent University branch
- · Conducted selection tests, incl. reasoning tests and structured interviews, of about 70 university students
- Other activities: implementation of 180° feedback system, social media marketing, event support

**180 Degrees Consulting** 

Ghent, BE Mar. 2015 - Jun. 2015

Jul. 2015 - Jun. 2016

· Co-developed an integrated fundraising and marketing strategy for the NGO 'Join For Water'

- Conducted survey research regarding the brand perceptions of Join For Water's donors and sympathizers
- · Developed an evidence-based, bespoke brand personality for Join For Water, as well as brand improvement guidelines

# **Education**

MANAGEMENT CONSULTANT

HR DIRECTOR

**Ghent University** Ghent RF

Aug. 2019 - Present PhD. Economics

- Doctoral courses: Econometrics, Advanced Econometrics (Non-Linear Techniques), Labour Economics, Multilevel Analysis
- Other courses: Advanced Academic Writing in English, Multilevel Analysis in R, Generalised Linear Models in R, Multidisciplinary Research Tools to Study Work and the Labour Market, Effective Graphical Displays
- Supervisors: Prof. Stijn Baert, Prof. Eva Derous

Vrije Universiteit Brussel Brussels, BE

Aug. 2019 - Present PhD, Sociology

- · Supervisor: Prof. Pieter-Paul Verhaeghe
- Joint PhD with Ghent University as the main institution

**Vlerick Business School** Ghent BF

MM, GENERAL MANAGEMENT (MAGNA CUM LAUDE)

Sep. 2016 - Jun. 2017

- · Key Courses: Corporate Finance, Financial Accounting, Management Accounting and Control, Strategic Management, Operations Management • Electives: Big Data and Data Analytics, Digital Strategy (w/BNPP Fortis), Strategy and Organisational Design, Mergers and Acquisitions (w/Gimv)
- Bootcamp: Strategic Innovation in Renewable Energy (w/ Durabilis)

**Ghent University** Ghent. BE

MSc, Industrial and Organisational Psychology (Magna Cum Laude)

Sep. 2011 - Jun. 2016

- · Key Courses: Multi-level Organisational Research, Statistics, Applied Data Analysis, Human Resource Management, Industrial Relations
- Master's thesis: Short form of the Wilde Intelligenztest: Psychometric qualities and utility of a 12-minute intelligence test for personnel selection

# **Publications**

# **TECHNICAL REPORTS**

2021 **Ghent University** 

Discriminatie op de Gentse arbeidsmarkt anno 2021: rapportering

S Baert, A Dalle, L Lippens, L Malfait

**Ghent University** 2021

Nulmeting discriminatie op de Antwerpse arbeidsmarkt: rapportering

S Baert, A Dalle, L Lippens, L Malfait, A Sharipova

# **DISCUSSION PAPERS**

#### 2021 **IZA Institute of Labour Economics**

The state of hiring discrimination: A meta-analysis of (almost) all recent correspondence experiments L Lippens, S Vermeiren, S Baert

#### PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

2022	Applied	<b>Economics</b>	Letters
2022	Applica	Econoniuc3	ECCCC13

Ethnic discrimination on paper: Uncovering realtors' willingness to discriminate with mystery mails

A Ghekiere, L Lippens, S Baert, PP Verhaeghe

Journal of Ethnic and Migration Studies

Is labour market discrimination against ethnic minorities better explained by taste or statistics? A systematic

review of the empirical evidence

L Lippens, S Baert, A Ghekiere, PP Verhaeghe, E Derous

2021 **Economics Letters** 

Loss aversion in taste-based employee discrimination: Evidence from a choice experiment

L Lippens, S Baert, E Derous

2021 PLOS ONE

How do employees think the COVID-19 crisis will affect their careers?

L Lippens, E Moens, P Sterkens, J Weytjens, S Baert

2021 The European Journal of Health Economics

The COVID-19 crisis and telework: A research survey on experiences, expectations and hopes

E Moens, L Lippens, P Sterkens, J Weytjens, S Baert

Visit my Google Scholar profile at https://bit.ly/louis-lippens-scholar for a comprehensive overview of my research.

# Services and Outreach

#### PEER REVIEWS

In addition to conducting my own research, I have also reviewed the work of some of my peers. I have served as a reviewer (ad hoc) for the Journal of Labor Economics (1), Work and Occupations (1), Social Science & Medicine (1), Social Forces (1), Journal of Sociology (1) PLOS ONE (2), International Migration Review (1), Social Policy and Society (1), Oxford Bulletin of Economics and Statistics (1), International Journal of Manpower (1), and Economics Bulletin (2).

#### SOCIETAL OUTREACH

2022	UGent @ Work	Blog post
	Ethnic labour market discrimination: Generalisation or aversion?	blog post
2022	HR Magazine	Magazino articlo
	Structured interview best predicts a good match	Magazine article
2022	UGent @ Work	Stony
	Inactivity among migrants in Belgium	Story
2022	UGent @ Work	Cton
	Inactivity in Europe and the Belgian Regions	Story
2022	LinkedIn	Dlagmost
	The top-ranked selection tools to hire the best-performing candidate	Blog post
2021	Het Laatste Nieuws	Namananarartiala
	Older applicants face greater hiring discrimination than ethnic minority applicants worldwide	Newspaper article
2021	Trends (magazine)	Namananarartiala
	Hiring discrimination based on age is worse than ethnic hiring discrimination	Newspaper article
2021	UGent @ Work	Dlanast
	Does discrimination have a price?	Blog post
2021	Radio 1, Nieuwe Feiten	Dardia internieno
	Does discrimination have a price?	Radio interview
2020	Apache	Managara
	Trainings against labour market discrimination	Newspaper article
2020	Het Laatste Nieuws	
	My job disappears, my pay gets smaller, my promotion gets snubbed: This is how the Flemish people think	Newspaper article
	about their work future	

# ACADEMIC OUTREACH

2022	IMISCOE Annual Conference	Oclo NO	
	The state of hiring discrimination: A meta-analysis of (almost) all recent correspondence experiments	Oslo, NO	
2022	Spring Meeting of Young Economists	Orléans, FR	
	The state of hiring discrimination: A meta-analysis of (almost) all recent correspondence experiments	Oneans, FR	
2021	CESSMIR PhD Meeting	Chant DE	
	The state of hiring discrimination: A meta-analysis of (almost) all recent correspondence experiments	Ghent, BE	
2021	EALE Annual Conference	Barcelona, ES	
	Is labour market discrimination against ethnic minorities better explained by taste or statistics?	(online)	
2021	Day of Sociology	Utrecht, NL	
	Taste-based discrimination: Actually a matter of contact avoidance?	(online)	
2021	CESSMIR Research Day	Ghent, BE	
	Taste-based discrimination: Actually a matter of contact avoidance?	GHEIR, DL	
2021	Faculty of Economics and Business Administration Research Day	Chant DE	
	Loss aversion in taste-based employee discrimination: Evidence from a choice experiment	Ghent, BE	
2020	Context Matters Symposium	Brussels, BE	
	Is labour market discrimination against ethnic minorities better explained by taste or statistics?	DIUSSEIS, DE	

# Skills\_\_\_\_\_

# GENERAL SKILLS

Research	Analytics	Business
Audit studies – Survey research – Experimental research – Applied psychometrics	Linear models – (Ordered) logit models – Meta-analysis – Meta-regression – Reliability and validity analysis – Structural equation modeling	Project management – Human capital management – Corporate finance – Consultancy

# TECHNICAL SKILLS

Coding Languages	Research Software	Business Software	Creative Software	Other
R (ggplot2, tidyverse, hugo, xaringan, quarto) – SQL	RStudio – Stata – SPSS – Knime	Collibra – MS Office	Photoshop – GIMP – Ableton Live	Git – Markdown – LaTeX

# LANGUAGES

Skill	Dutch	English	French
Reading	C2	C2	C1
Writing	C2	C2	B2
Listening	C2	C2	C1
Speaking	C2	C1	B1

Note. CEFR: A1/A2: Basic User; B1/B2: Independent User; C1/C2: Proficient User.

# Certificates \_\_\_\_\_

2019	Exploratory Data Analysis (Johns Hopkins University)	Coursera
2018	Reproducible Research (Johns Hopkins University)	Coursera
2019	R Programming (Johns Hopkins University)	Coursera
2017	Financial Markets (Yale University)	Coursera
2017	Fundamentals of Quantitative Modeling (Wharton School)	Coursera
2017	Collibra Community Manager	Collibra
2017	Collibra Data Steward	Collibra

# **Honors and Awards**

#### 2017 **Student Achievement for Outstanding Performance**

Vlerick Business Personal recognition for obtaining the most and highest positive peer evaluations in group assignments throughout the academic year.

#### 2015 **Best European Consulting Branch**

180 Degrees Consulting Ghent was named the best overall European branch (Europe) of the world's largest consultancy for non-profits and social enterprises. We were lauded for our collaboration-fostering spirit, high client focus and professional approach to private partnerships.

180 Degrees Consulting

School

# Trivia

#### **Sucker for R**

I am a sucker for everything related to R (ggplot2, Shiny, Xaringan...), my go-to environment for statistical computing. The content of this very resume is written in R, using R Markdown, the {{vitae}} package, and some LaTeX typesetting.

#### Passionate about electronic music

I have been playing the piano since I was 9 years old, albeit much less frequently in the past few years. Moreover, between the ages of 15 and 22, I was active as an electronic music artist, producer, and event manager.

#### Fond of the sea

As a teenager, I longed to spend my summer vacations at the seaside. From my 18th birthday onwards, after an intensive year of training, I was able to combine this fondness for the sea with a student job as a lifeguard at the Belgian coast for 6 consecutive summers.